# JASON M LARKIN

4763 Sherwood Dr. Pittsburgh PA 15236 • (412) 398-8813 • jasonlarkin84@gmail.com • http://jasonlarkin.github.io

#### CAREER OVERVIEW AND OBJECTIVE

I have extensive experience performing experimental and numerical studies in condensed matter physics. My interests include multi-language development for applications ranging from high-performance parallel computing to smart phones, and open-source collaboration to improve the way research is performed and the way results are disseminated.

### **EDUCATION**

Carnegie Mellon University Pittsburgh, PA • PhD Mechanical Engineering, 2013 GPA: 3.85/4.00

**Thesis: Thermal Modeling of Disordered Materials.** Numerically investigated thermal properties of crystal alloys, glasses, and organic materials using classical and *ab initio*-based atomistic techniques.

Coursework: molecular/electron structure · nanoscale transport phenomena · numerical methods

University of Pittsburgh Pittsburgh, PA • MS Mechanical Engineering, 2009 GPA: 3.70/4.00

**Thesis: Statistics of Particle Concentrations in Free-Surface Turbulence.** Performed experiments using novel 2D and 3D flow configurations to study turbulence as a nonlinear dynamical system.

Coursework: quantum and statistical physics · turbulence · chaos and nonlinear phenomena

University of Pittsburgh Pittsburgh, PA • BS Mechanical Engineering, 2007 GPA: 3.20/4.00

Research: Used computational fluid dynamics to design a model arterial bifurcation for in vivo study.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

### Carnegie Mellon University (2010-2012) Teaching Assistant-Heat Transfer

• Topics in conduction, convection, and radiation. Supervised recitations and substituted for lectures.

### University of Pittsburgh (2008) Teaching Assistant-Advanced Fluid Mechanics

• Topics in viscous flow, boundary layer theory, and scale similarity.

### University of Pittsburgh (2007-2009) Lecturer-Physics

• Lectured to students and faculty on mathematics, bio-physics, turbulence, statistical and nonlinear phenomena.

### Precision Therapeutics (2006-2007) Intern-Technology Development

- Worked with team of software developers and laboratory equipment specialists.
- Used CADD to design and fabricate components of optical microscopes and laboratory automation controls.

### SKILLS

- Computing Languages: Matlab, Fortran, Python, C/C++, Java, LaTEX, Shell, Perl, Markdown, HTML.
- **High-Performance Computing:** linux/unix cluster administration/computing, parallel computation (MPI, OpenMP), mixed-language development, open-source development (Git, Github, arXiv).
- General Computing: linux/unix, Mac OS, Windows, Microsoft Office.
- Modeling: atomistic simulation, quantum chemistry, nanoscale transport, statistical and nonlinear systems.
- Hardware: general computing, optics/lasers, DI/DO AI/AO interfaces, simple automation, machining, circuitry.

### **PROJECTS**

- Quantum Mechanics-Driven Prediction of Nanostructure Thermal Conductivity: served as investigator under the AFOSR with collaborators at Carnegie Mellon and Univ. of Pitt., performing calculations on the DOD's HPCMP.
- disorder: a comprehensive repository of open-source code and data from my PhD thesis, hosted on Github.
- ntpy: created this open-source collaborative effort between members of NTPL and University of Toronto.
- GULP: international collaboration with Julian Gale at the Nanochemistry Research Institute at Curtin University.
- Statistics of Free-Surface Turbulence: international collaboration with Alain Pumir at ENS Lyon, France.

### PUBLICATIONS (SELECTED)

- "Origin of the Exceptionally Low Thermal Conductivity of Fullerene Derivative PCBM Films", (in progress).
- "Decorrelating a Compressible Turbulent Flow: an Experiment", Phys. Rev. E 82, 016301 (2010).

## PRESENTATIONS (SELECTED)

- "Evaluation of the Virtual Crystal Approximation for Predicting Thermal Conductivity", J.M. Larkin (speaker), A.J.H. McGaughey, 2013 MRS Spring Meeting San Francisco, CA.
- "The Generalized Fractal Dimensions of a 2-D Compressible Turbulence", J. Larkin (speaker), M. Bandi, W. Goldburg, 2008 American Physical Society March Meeting New Orleans, LA.

## Honors

- 2012 ASME MHNMT International Summer Heat Transfer Conference Top 5 Technical Paper
- 2011 Bennett Conference Best Presentation
- 2011 ICES Northrop-Gruman Fellow
- 2007-2009 NSF Graduate Student Research Grant University of Pittsburgh Deptartment of Physics.

### **M**EMBERSHIPS

 American Physical Society · American Society of Mechanical Engineers · Materials Research Society · Society of Industrial and Applied Mathematics · DOD High Performance Computing Modernization Program